these two Foods or more accurately
stated ingestible substances that really
do melt visceral fat the most harmful
fat on your body in fact this study that
I'll show you might begin to change my
mind about something fundamental that I
believed or still believe this is the
study that researchers split people
randomly into three nutrition groups one
group consumed a healthy diet guidelines
diet which is just a General balanced
diet recommending Whole Foods limiting
saturated fat and sugar and focusing on
vegetables fruits and whole grains the
second diet was a Mediterranean diet
focused on reducing simple carbohydrates
increased unsaturated fats and the third
diet was the Mediterranean diet but
including two additions green tea and
wolfia globosa also called duckweed
duckweed is a high fiber high protein
plant most common to Asia this nutrition
condition was dubbed the green Med
condition now there were some additional
key differences between the nutrition
groups one only the Mediterranean diets
were on a supposed calorie deficit not
the healthy dietary guidelines control
diet in addition the Mediterranean diet
including the green tea and the duckweed
so the green Med replac their protein
with plant protein from this duck wheat
of note there were no significant
differences across the groups say for
women in the green Med Group had
slightly lower visceral body fat than in
the other two groups but the men were
the same in that regard the study was
well-powered with almost 300
participants the study ran for a year
and a half and all groups were also
encouraged to participate in the same
exercise program so what happened as
usual let's crack open the data we can
see the results the green is the green
Med diet the blue is the normal
Mediterranean diet and the red is the
healthy diet guidelines control diet the
vat change there is the visceral fat the
type of body fat that infiltrates and
surrounds our organs and is heavily
connected to disease so the less the
better here the researchers are
measuring the amount of visceral fat
reduction from Baseline to 18 months
later the asterisks under each bar
indicate a statistically significant
difference in a Within in diet
comparison so just indicating
improvement over time for each diet
individually however the P values above
indicate a between Diet comparison the
cut off for statistical significance was
0.05 so anything under that indicates a
likely effect so interestingly all diets
led to an improvement in visceral fat
which is wonderful to see especially
since only two of the groups were
encouraged to be in a calorie deficit it
however by ey and by statistic the green
Med diet outperformed both other diets
indicating a mere addition of these two
substances led to significantly more
visceral fat loss in fact around three
times more I'll show you images in a
minute first what are these other
results here we're looking at
subcutaneous fat or fat that sits right
under the skin layer this type of fat is
less dangerous than visceral fat and
interestingly again all three diets
reduce it and there is a trend in the
data again favoring the green Med
condition although it's only the deeper
regions of the subcutaneous fat this
might again indicate that these
compounds specifically Target a type of
fat that is more dangerous which is just
wildly cool let's get to the images of
the visceral fat in MRI scans and also
which factors in the diet were most
strongly linked to this Improvement in
visceral fat also there's more to say on
the exercise routine the green tea and
the duckweed a few other details like
the 10year risk of cardiovascular
disease that don't fit into this video
so I'm adding it to the extended version
of this video which is available for the
physionic Insiders my premium research
review including podcasts a premium
Community Access to all my analyses
shortened summaries a premium email list
and more it's a Ste if I may well biasly
say it's linked in the description box
hope to see you there here are the
images of the visceral fat and there's
something here that really opened up my
eyes to something that I never believed
before those are MRI scans across all
three diet conditions for Baseline on
top to 18 months later bottom the green
is the visceral fat and the Quantified
values are at the bottom again we
confirm that vat loss that's visceral
fat was greatest in the green Med
condition however one aspect that I was
skeptical about was the fact that the
researchers failed to measure calorie
intake yes I mentioned before that
calorie intake was reduced for both
Mediterranean diets yet it wasn't
actually measured in fact they were
given a range of calories to aim for
which leaves more room for air so my
question was is the visceral fat loss
from the green tea and the duckweed or
was it from the greater weight loss due
to the greater calorie deficit the
answer is at least in part here my
initial belief was that a calorie
deficit was the major if not only way to
Target a subset of fat however if you
look at the amount of weight loss
between the Mediterranean diets it's the
same yet the visceral fat loss is double
in the green condition this suggests
that the effects are independent of
caloric intake as caloric intake was
likely s similar and the effects are
likely driven by the two
consumables one more word of caution
this still isn't Fool Proof because
we're looking at representative people's
images not the average result across 300
participants but assuming that this
holds true this opens my mind to the
idea that calories are not the only
primary driver of visceral fat loss okay
but speaking to that the researchers
Quantified some associations with
different factors that could contribute
to this outsized visceral fat loss for
example looking at total polyphenol
count in the blood of partipants we see
the amount of visceral fat loss on the
horizontal axis and we see three
different levels of blood polyphenols in
ascending order so the greater ones
polyphenol levels are the greater the
association to visceral fat loss
relative to low polyphenol levels
polyphenols are naturally occurring
molecules found in plants that are
belief to play a role in protecting the
body through antioxidant abilities
anti-inflammatory abilities and more
let's look at some other associations
like here here we see that less red meat
consumption up top is linked to Greater
reductions in visceral fat than less red
meat or if we look at one of the main
ingredients monai consumption which is
the duckweed I.E wolfia globosa there's
an association with reduced visceral fat
with greater monai consumption Makai
consumption it's one of those these
associations are adjusted for sex and
age so they aren't adjusted enough to
make definitive claims as there's plenty
of room for other variables to explain
these results so where does that leave
us what to do well here are the
takeaways one we know a healthier diet
focused on Whole Foods plus exercise
improves visceral fat modestly
two a more potent diet that triples
visceral fat loss is a calorie
restricted Mediterranean diet including
daily green tea and wolfia globosa I.E
duckweed consumption that said if you're
interested in understanding how visceral
fat contributes to disease you should
check out this video on the personal fat
threshold and another way of reversing
visceral fat